Guide to the Williams Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Williams family papers
1711-1930
1724-1800
GEN MSS 1180
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.96
(3 boxes)
The Williams Family Papers consists of correspondence, writings, documents, and financial records kept by descendants of William Williams who lived in and near Wethersfield, Connecticut, in the eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries. The papers are those of Elisha Williams, his second wife Elizabeth Scott Williams Smith, and his nephew Ezekiel Williams, merchant and sheriff of Hartford County. The correspondence is with family members and associates; the writings consist of sermons and essays by family members; documents are primarily related to the settlement of Elizabeth Smith's estate in the United States and England. Other papers include an engraved circular letter from London publisher James Rivington advertising a new edition of a work by Philip Doddridge.
Williams family
Parsons, Francis, 1871-1937
Smith, Elizabeth Scott Williams, 1708-1776
Williams, Elisha, 1694-1755
Williams, Ezekiel, 1729-1818
Williams, Solomon, 1700-1776
Williams, Thomas Scott, 1777-1861
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Francis Parsons (Yale BA 1893, LLB 1897, MA (Hon) 1925), 1937. Other additions are noted at the folder level.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Williams Family of Connecticut and Massachusetts
The papers in this collection were largely donated by Francis Parsons of Hartford, Connecticut, and document his ancestors from five generations above him, all descendants of Robert Williams (1608-1693) and his wife Elizabeth Stalham (1595-1674), who emigrated from England to Roxbury, Massachusetts, in the seventeenth century. Their son Isaac Williams (1638-1709) had a son William Williams (1665-1741), and it is the two sons of William Williams, Elisha (1694-1755) and Solomon (1701-1776), and their descendants, whose papers are present here. These families were prominent citizens and religious leaders in and around Wethersfield, a town south of Hartford. Much of the information about the family was taken from The Ancestors and Descendants of Ezekiel Williams of Wethersfield, 1608-1907, by Mary Dyer Williams McLean (Privately printed, 1907). The principals in the papers are the following family members:
Elisha Williams (1694-1755), fourth child born to William Williams and his first wife Elizabeth Cotton Williams (1665–1698), was a Congregational minister, legislator, militia soldier, jurist, and the fourth rector of Yale College (1726-1739). He married twice, first in 1714 to Eunice Chester (died 1750), with whom he had six children, and second to Elizabeth Scott in 1751.
Elizabeth Scott Williams Smith (1708-1776) was the daughter of Thomas Scott (1680-1746), independent minister at Norwich, England. A poet and hymnist, she married Elisha Williams in 1751 and moved with him to Connecticut. In 1761 she married a prominent New York jurist, William Smith (1697-1769) and lived in New York City. After his death she returned to Wethersfield to reside at the home of Ezekiel Williams, the nephew of her first husband, until her death there on June 13, 1776.
Ezekiel Williams (1729-1818), son of Reverend Solomon Williams (1701-1776) and Mary Porter Williams (1703-1787), was a merchant in Wethersfield and sheriff of Hartford County from 1767 to 1789. He was married to Prudence Stoddard (1734-1822), with whom he had eleven children.
Francis Parsons (1871-1937), the donor of the papers, was the son of John Caldwell Parsons (1832-1898) and Mary McClellan (1844-1871). He was a banker, lawyer, and author in Hartford. and the great-great-grandson of Ezekiel Williams (1729-1818).
Williams Family Tree
Family members appearing in the papers are underlined.
Robert Williams (1608-1693) m Elizabeth Stalham (1595-1674); 7 children, including
--2 Isaac Williams (1638-1709) m1 1660 Martha Park (1641-1674), m2 Judith Cooper; 12 children including
----3 WILLIAM WILLIAMS (1665-1741) m1 1686 Elizabeth Cotton (1665–1698); m2 1699 Christian Stoddard (1676-1764)
------4 William Williams (1687-1687)
------4 William Williams (1688-1760)
------4 Martha Williams (1690-1766) m Edward Partridge
------4 ELISHA WILLIAMS (1694-1755) m1 1714 Eunice Chester (died 1750), m2 1751 ELIZABETH SCOTT (1708-1776)
--------5 Eunice Williams (1716-1741)
--------5 Elisha Williams (1717-1784) m1 1742 Prudence Robbins, m2 1749 Mehitable Burnham; 7 children
--------5 Samuel Williams (1720-1740)
--------5 William Williams (1722-1741)
--------5 Anne Williams (1731-1750)
--------5 Mary Williams (1735-1776) m Eliphalet Williams (1726-1803); 5 children
------4 John Williams (1697-1697)
------4 SOLOMON WILLIAMS (1701-1776) m 1723 Mary Porter (1703-1787)
--------5 Solomon Williams (1723-1723)
--------5 Solomon Williams (1725-1743)
--------5 Eliphalet Williams (1726-1803) m Mary Williams (1735-1776); 5 children
--------5 EZEKIEL WILLIAMS (1729-1818) m 1760 Prudence Stoddard (1734-1822)
----------6 Emily Williams (1761-1850) m 1785 Samuel William Williams (died 1812); 11 children
----------6 John Williams (1762-1840) m1 Sophia Worthington (1765-1813), m2 Mary Dyer Silliman; 9 children
----------6 HARRIET WILLIAMS (1764-1850) m David Parsons (1748-1823); 11 children including
------------7 Francis Parsons (1795-1861) m Clarissa Brown; 4 children including
--------------8 John Caldwell Parsons (1832-1898) m 1870 Mary McClellan (1844-1871)
----------------9 FRANCIS PARSONS (1871-1937) m 1897 Elizabeth Alden Hutchins (1872-)
----------6 Ezekiel Williams (1765-1843) m Abigail Ellsworth (1774-1860); 1 child
----------6 Prudence Williams (1767-1853) m Bezaleel Howard (1753-1837); 4 children
----------6 Mary Williams (1769-1850) m John Salter (1769-1831); 12 children
----------6 Esther Williams (1771-1820); unmarried
----------6 Solomon Stoddard Williams (1773-1840); unmarried
----------6 Christian Williams (1775-1803); unmarried
----------6 Thomas Scott Williams (1777-1861) m1 1812 Delia Ellsworth (1789-1840), m2 Martha Coit (d. 1867); no children
----------6 Samuel Porter Williams (1779-1826); m1 Mary H. Webb (d. 1815), m2 Sarah P. Tyler; 13 children
--------5 William Williams (1731-1811) m Mary Trumbull (1745-1831)
--------5 Mary Williams (1733-1794) m Richard Salter
--------5 Thomas Williams (1735-1819) m Rebecca Welles
--------5 Christiana Williams (1738-) m John Salter
--------5 Moses Williams (1740-1750)
--------5 Samuel Williams (1741-1742)
--------5 Eunice Williams (1745-1836) m Timothy Stone
------4 Elizabeth Williams (1707-1753) m Samuel Barnard
------4 Israel Williams (1709-1788)
--------5 William Williams (1734-1808)
------4 Dorothy Williams (1713-1808) m Jonathan Ashley
Scope and Contents
The Williams Family Papers consists of correspondence, documents, and financial records kept by descendants of William Williams who lived in and near Wethersfield, Connecticut, in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. The papers include those of Elisha Williams, his second wife Elizabeth Scott Williams Smith, and his nephew Ezekiel Williams, merchant and sheriff of Hartford County.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Elisha Williams Papers, 1711-1759. II. Elizabeth Scott Williams Smith Papers, 1735-1775. III. Ezekiel Williams Papers, 1751-1812. IV. Other Papers, 1724-1930.
Clergy -- Connecticut; Women -- Connecticut; Connecticut -- History -- 1775-1865; Connecticut -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Connecticut -- Politics and government -- 1775-1865; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Almanacs -- United States -- 18th century; Circular letters -- England -- London -- 18th century; Estate records -- United States -- 18th century; Sermons -- United States -- 18th century; Wills -- United States -- 18th century; Clergy -- Connecticut -- 18th century; Bronson, Isaac, 1760-1838; Clap, Thomas, 1703-1767; Doddridge, Philip, 1702-1751; Keteltas, Abraham, 1732-1798; Lockwood, James, 1714-1772; Parsons, Francis, 1871-1937; Rivington, James, 1724-1802; Scott, Thomas, 1680-1746; Smith, Elizabeth Scott Williams, 1708-1776; Williams, Elisha, 1694-1755; Williams, Ezekiel, 1729-1818; Williams family; Williams, Solomon, 1700-1776; Williams, Stephen, 1693-1782; Williams, Thomas Scott, 1777-1861
- Elisha Williams Papers, 1711-1759; Series I; 18
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into four subseries: Incoming Letters, Outgoing Letters, Other Letters, Other Papers.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains letters to and from Elisha Williams, notably twenty-six letters from Williams to his cousin Stephen Williams (1693-1782), while the latter was a student at Harvard College and afterward a resident at Hadley, Massachusetts; Stephen was the son of Reverend John Williams of Deerfield, Massachusetts, and was held captive by the Abenakis Indians in Canada for more than a year as a child. Also present are several sermons written by Elisha Williams.
  - Incoming letters
    - Doddridge, Philip, 1751 Apr 4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Dwight, Joseph, 1752 Jun 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Smith, Elizabeth Scott Williams, 1754, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Williams, Israel, 1752 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Williams, Solomon, 1740-1750 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Outgoing letters
    - Ingersoll, Jared, 1753 Feb 23 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Williams, Solomon, 1735 Dec 30 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Williams, Stephen, 1711-1714, 1724 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Custodial History
      Letters of 1711-1714 gift of Lemuel Welles, 1939; letter of 1724 gift of Anson P. Stokes, 1937.
  - Other letters
    - William Williams (1665-1741) to his grandsons Elisha, Solomon, and Eliphalet Williams, 1739, 1741 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Other papers
    - Deed for sale of land in Wethersfield from Nathaniel Burnham to Elisha Williams (1717-1784), 1759 Apr 30 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Drafts of letters, notes about army problems, draft of codicil to will (4 pages), 1749, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Essay, "The Doctrine of the Publick Covenant between God and his People", 1713 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Gift of Lemuel A. Welles, 1939.
    - Last will and testament, 1755
    - Letter of recommendation, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Report of sermons preached in New Haven, 1729-1730, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Anonymous gift.
    - Sermons and fragments (14), circa 1721-1725 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Gift of Grace Treadwell, 1930
    - Sermons (7), 1722-1743, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Sermon, 1724 Sep 27 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Given to Alexander Joseph Sessions (Yale BA 1831, MA 1845) by John Stoddard Williams (Yale 1827) and then to Benjamin Osgood Peirce; gift of Isabella Landreth Peirce, 1922.
    - Sermon, 1745 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Elizabeth Scott Williams Smith Papers, 1735-1775; Series II; 20
  Series II is organized into four subseries: Incoming Letters, Outgoing Letters, Third-party Letters, and Other Papers.
  The series contains correspondence and other papers of Elizabeth Scott Williams Smith. The correspondence is primarily incoming from both the Scotts, her family in England, and the Williams family in Connecticut, the brothers and other relations of her first husband Elisha Williams. Notable are fourteen letters from her brother-in-law Rev. Solomon Williams, and four from her brother Thomas Scott, poet, hymnist, and minister at Ipswich; third-party correspondence includes a letter from Smith's father Thomas Scott to another Nonconformist preacher, Rev. Philip Doddridge (1702-1751) of Northampton, England. Also present are three of Smith's autograph manuscript poems.
  Papers related to the settlement of Elizabeth Smith's estates in England and the United States are filed in Series III.
  - Incoming letters
    - Baker, Rebeckah, 1753 Feb 22 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Dwight, Joseph, 1755 Aug 2 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Hague, Elizabeth Scott, 1769-1774 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Scott, Daniel (1694-1759, uncle), undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
      General
      19th-century manuscript copy of two letters dated 1750 and 1755.
    - Scott, John (brother), 1752-1767 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Scott, Mary (step-grandmother, second wife of Daniel Scott Sr.), 1743-1747 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Scott, Thomas (1680-1746, father), 1735, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Scott, Thomas (1705-1775, brother), 1750-1771 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Williams, Elisha, 1753-1754 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Williams, Ezekiel, 1761, 1768 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Williams, Israel, 1755 Jul 26 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Williams, Solomon, 1757-1774 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Outgoing letters
    - Harper, Mrs., undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Scott, Thomas (1680-1746, father), undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Third-party letters
    - Church of Christ, Norwich, England, to James Lockwood, Church of Christ, Wethersfield, 1751 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      Regarding Elizabeth Scott Williams's move from one congregation to the other.
    - Daniel Scott to Thomas Scott, 1740 Apr 22 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Philip Doddridge to Thomas Scott, 1740 May 26 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Thomas Scott to Philip Doddridge, 1745 Apr 17 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      Purchased on the Azariah Eldridge Memorial Fund, 1916.
  - Other papers
    - Poems, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
      Contains: "The Christian Hero," "Family Religion," and "Seeking a New Habitation."
    - Business papers, including notes, bills, agreements, 1760-1775 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Ezekiel Williams Papers, 1751-1812; Series III; 26
  Series III is organized into four subseries: Incoming Letters, Outgoing Letters, Third-party Letters, and Other Papers.
  The series contains correspondence and other material related to Ezekiel Williams's family and his career as sheriff of Hartford County. Also present are some papers of his son Thomas Scott Williams (1777-1861), including letters from Williams to Thomas when he was a student at Yale College, and two of his school essays.
  Notable in this series are three files documenting the estate of William's uncle's second wife, Elizabeth Scott Williams Smith (see Series II), which include her wills, correspondence related to bequests, and financial records for settling the estate in England and the United States.
  - Incoming letters
    - Barnard, Samuel, 1755 Sep 3 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Bronson, Isaac, 1791 Sep 7 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Chauncey, Charles, 1789 May 9 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Goodrich, Chauncey, 1812 Nov 19 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Hancock, Margaret, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
      Governess for Ezekiel Williams's children; includes three proposed epitaphs for her tombstone, one in the hand of Ezekiel Williams.
    - Howard, Bezaleel, 1795, 1805 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Lake, Mary, 1789 Sep 15 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Salter, Richard, 1786 Sep 20 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Tuthill, Jane Hancock, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Williams, Elisha, 1755 Apr 4 (Box 2, Folder 48)
      With undated autograph note at bottom by Mary D. McLean.
    - Williams, William (1731-1811, brother), 1776 Feb 12 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Williams, William (1734-1808, cousin), 1759, 1791 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Outgoing letters
    - Dwight, Elijah, 1774 Jan 4 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Williams, Thomas Scott, 1791-1794 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Wolcott, Oliver, 1788 Aug 6 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Third-party correspondence
    - Samuel M. Hopkins to Thomas Scott Williams, 1800 Jan 2 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Harriet Williams Parsons to Thomas Scott Williams, 1797 Sep (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Other papers
    - Astronomical Diary and Almanack (Boston: J. Draper, 1751) (Box 2, Folder 56)
      Includes Williams' autograph manuscript diary annotations.
    - Elizabeth Scott Williams Smith estate papers, 1773-1796 (Box 2, Folder 57-59)
      Ezekiel Williams served as executor for his aunt's estate; the files contain her autograph will, manuscript copies of and a codicil to the will, an excerpt from William Smith's will, correspondence, invoices, and receipts.
    - Gravestone inscription for Solomon Williams, circa 1776 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Legal and other documents related to personal and professional business, 1753-1805 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Mary Hooker estate papers, 1783 (Box 2, Folder 62)
      Related to sale of land to Ezekiel Williams.
    - Release note from John Chester to Van Horne Lott, 1785 Jul 12 (Box 2, Folder 63)
      Requesting that Chester's decanters and wine glasses be delivered to Ezekiel Williams.
    - Thomas Scott Williams essays on Homer and Milton, 1796 (Box 2, Folder 64)
- Other Papers, 1724-1930; Series IV; 14
  Series IV is organized into four subseries: Documents, Letters by Others, Writings by Others, Francis Parsons Papers.
  The series contains papers that could not be directly attached to the people in Series I-III, but were found with the collection, including an engraved circular letter from James Rivington & Co. dated 1759. The fourth subseries, Francis Parsons Papers, contains letters to the donor of the collection regarding the family and their papers.
  - Documents
    - Contract for the sale of sloop Olive to Thomas by William Laight and Frederick Rhinelander, 1773 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Circular letter from James Rivington Co. regarding a new edition of Philip Doddridge's Family Expositor, 1759 Oct 13 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Letter of recommendation for James Lockwood for license to preach the gospel, 1736 Dec 22 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - William Williams (1731-1811) clipped autographs (2), undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Letters by others
    - Andrew Adams to Stephen Mitchell, 1789 Jul 22 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Samuel Davies to Joseph Forfitt, August 26, 1758; manuscript copy, undated (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Samuel Johnson to John Beach, 1724 Apr 3 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Solomon Williams to Thomas Clap, 1752 Feb 13 (Box 2, Folder 72)
      Gift of Elizabeth Cutler Woodward, 1951.
  - Writings by others
    - "An Essay on Original Sin" by John Arthur, 1766 Feb (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Minutes of the General Meeting of the Society for the Propagation of the Gospel in Foreign Parts, 1735 May 16 (Box 2, Folder 74)
      Manuscript copy by David Humphreys; minutes refer to William Williams.
    - Two sermons, author unidentified, England, 1734-1735 (Box 2, Folder 75)
      Dated Aylsham, 1734, and Lowestoft, June 1735; likely related to Thomas Scott or his son.
    - Three sermons by Solomon Williams, 1764, 1772 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Francis Parsons papers
    - Correspondence
      - Giffard, Hardinge F., 1890 (Box 2, Folder 77)
      - McLean, Mary Dyer Williams, to Francis and John Caldwell Parsons, 1890-1903 (Box 2, Folder 78)
        Contains a transcript of a letter from Philip Doddridge to Elizabeth Scott Williams Smith, March 21, 1745.
      - Williams, Edward H., 1903 Jan 27 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Elizabeth Scott Williams Smith material, circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 80)
      Includes typed transcripts of her published obituary (1776), a letter from her to Eliphalet Williams (1765), and photographs of a mirror and portrait she owned.
- Oversize, 3
  - In Series I: Last will and testament, 1755 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 81)
  - In Series II: John Scott to Elizabeth Scott Williams Smith, 1752 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 82)
  - In Series II:. Solomon Williams to Elizabeth Scott Williams Smith, 1762 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 83)